Clove Spring Iron Works
Marist College
Clove Spring Iron Works
1870-1904
NPKMC-219-191
3 Linear Feet
The Clove Spring Iron Works papers cover the day to day business operations of the company between the years 1870-1904. The papers include a variety of materials including business correspondence, telegraphs, contracts, legal documents, bills, receipts, checks, vouchers, deposit slips, balance sheets, payments, postcards, construction blueprints, paychecks, order records, invitations, tax receipts, weights of coal, price lists, account statements, lease agreements, insurance, and annual reports.
Marist College 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
Items in this collection do not circulate and may be used in-house only.
The Clove Spring Iron Works was a company founded in the late 1800s in Dutchess County, New York. The general manager of the company was John S. Schultze, who oversaw smaller companies that ran under the authority of the Clove Spring Iron Works including Sylvan Lake, the Clove Branch Railroad, and Newburgh, Dutchess, and Connecticut Railroad Company. The Clove Spring Iron Works was also managed by members of the Brown Family: George Brown (President) and Sam Brown (Treasurer). Other employees include William Reid (Secretary/Treasurer), Charles A. Taylor (Cashier), and H.B. Willits, an assistant to Schultze. The company also conducted its operations--mainly its orders--through the company store. Crocker Brothers, a manufacturing company, frequently ordered materials from Clove Spring Iron Works to produce metals. The Sylvan Lake mines were where the company extracted coal and ore which were used to manufacture iron products. Important employees at Sylvan Lake were Normal J Plass and C.A. Stephens who both served as treasurer, and E.W. Plass and Oliver Davidson who were both agents. Oliver Davidson also managed the East Fishkill Mills with Silvanus Davidson. The company transported coal and iron materials by the Newburgh, Dutchess, and Connecticut Railroad Company, which John S. Schultze managed until John Crosby Brown became the President in 1902. William Wells served as secretary/treasurer until H.H. Reed became the treasurer in 1902.The Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad Company worked with the president of the Philadelphia Reading and New England Railroad Company, John Brock, to transport to materials outside of the tri-state area.
The Clove Spring Iron Works papers cover the day to day business operations of the company between the years 1870-1904. The papers include a variety of materials including business correspondence, telegraphs, contracts, legal documents, bills, receipts, checks, vouchers, deposit slips, balance sheets, payments, postcards, construction blueprints, paychecks, order records, invitations, tax receipts, weights of coal, price lists, account statements, lease agreements, insurance, and annual reports.
Clove Spring
Series is arranged into thirteen series: 1) Finances, has four subseries, 2) Clove Spring Iron Works Company Store, has five subseries, 3) Brown Brothers, has three subseries, 4) Clove Branch Railroad, has three subseries, 5) Payroll, has seven subseries, 6) Correspondence, has five subseries, 7) Sylvan Lake, has three subseries, 8) Crocker Brothers, has two subseries, 9) Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad, has three subseries, 10) Administrative, has four subseries, 11) Operations, has ten subseries, 12) Coal, has twelve subseries, and 13) Miscellaneous, has three subseries
- 1. Finances, 1870-1904
  - Subseries 1.1: Bills, 1871-1902
    - Bills, 1871-1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bills, 1875-1878 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bills, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bills, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bills, 1881-1885 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bills, 1886-1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bills, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bills (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1.2: Receipted Bills, 1873-1892
    - Receipted Bills, 1873-1875 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Receipted Bills, 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Receipted Bills, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Receipted Bills, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Receipted Bills, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Receipted Bills, 1881-1886 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Receipted Bills, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 1.3: Correspondence, 1875-1891
    - Account Information, 1891-1891 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Request for Payment, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Requests for Account Balance, 1875-1881 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 1.4: Financial Documents, 1877-1891
    - Vouchers, 1877-1886 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Checks, 1871-1891 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Deposit Slips from Bank of NY, 1874-1878 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Balance Sheets and Statements, 1873-1878 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified Financial Calculations, 1873-1891 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- 2. Clove Spring Iron Works Company Store, 1873-1891
  - Subseries 2.1: Finances, 1873-1891
    - Correspondence Receipts, 1873-1879 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Receipts, 1880-1884 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Store Checks, 1874-1875 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Bils from William O. Mailler, 1879-1880 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2.2: Orders, 1872-1885
    - Correspondence Orders, 1872-1874 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence Orders, 1880-1888 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Orders with Eastmead, 1879-1885 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Orders with O. Davidson and co., 1872-1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Supply Orders, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Postcard Shipments, 1878-1885 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2.3: Statements of Orders, 1883
    - Orders March/April, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Orders May, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Orders June, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Orders July, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Orders August, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Orders September, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Orders October, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Orders November, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Orders December, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2.4: Contracts, 1874
    - Contract Regarding Payment Authorization, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Contract with Stopenell, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 2.5: Business Inquiries, 1872-1885
    - Business inquires, 1872-1878 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Business inquires, 1880-1885 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- 3. Brown Brothers, 1870-1892
  - Subseries 3.1: Finances, 1870-1892
    - Bills, 1870-1892 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Receipted Bills, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Receipted Bills, 1877-1879 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Sam Brown (treasurer), 1872-1873 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letters to Sam Brown (treasurer), 1874-1879 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3.2: Correspondence, 1871-1902
    - George Brown to Taylor, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - George Brown to Taylor, 1873-1874 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1871-1902 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 3.3: Miscellaneous, 1892
    - George Brown Real Estate Lease, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 4. Clove Branch Railroad, 1874-1903
  - Subseries 4.1: Finances, 1874-1881
    - Bills, 1879-1881 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Receipts and Receipted Bills, 1874-1881 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Payroll, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 4.2: Statements, 1877-1903
  - Subseries 4.3: Correspondence, 1874-1889
    - Meeting of the Board of Directors Invitations, 1881-1889 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Intra-company: capital stock, taxes, ore prices, 1874-1876 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Finances and Orders, 1874-1877 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Letters about number of cars, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Purchase Inquiry, 1875-1876 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- 5. Payroll, 1874-1903
  - Subseries 5.1: Reports, 1875-1885
    - Payroll, 1875-1876 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Payroll, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Payroll, May and June 1880 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Payroll, September, November, and December 1880 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Payroll, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Payroll, 1883-1884 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Subseries 5.2: Check Receipts, 1874-1886
    - Check receipts for payments in wages, charcoal, and jobs, 1874-1886 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Subseries 5.3: Employee Wages, 1881-1896
    - Employee Wages--Correspondence, 1881; 1884; 1896 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Subseries 5.4: Employee Requests, 1884-1886
    - Employee Requests, 1884-1886 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Subseries 5.5: Conflict, 1884-1896
    - Conflict with employee agreement and policies, 1884-1885; 1896 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Subseries 5.6: Job Inquiries, 1881-1885
    - Job Inquiries, 1881-1885 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Subseries 5.7: Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 33)
- 6. Correspondence, 1872-1889
  - Subseries 6.1: Charles Taylor (cashier), 1872-1874
    - I.N. Bartman, Furnace Architect and Builder, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - NY Boston and Montreal Railway Company, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Lyman Hall, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reed and Hoyt, Real Estate Brothers, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The Blake Crusher Company, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Edward Storm, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Office of the Continental Works, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - East Fishkill Mills, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Stissing National Bank, 1872-1874 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Taylor from Various, 1872-1874 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 6.2: Intra-company, 1872-1885
    - Schultze, 1877-1880 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Schultze, 1881-1885 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Taylor, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1872-1878 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 6.3: W.A. Reid (secretary and treasurer), 1872-1878
    - Schultze to Reid, 1874-1877 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Reid to Taylor, 1872-1873 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters to Reid, 1872-1878 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 6.4: Norman J. Plass (treasurer), 1873-1889
    - Schultze and Plass, 1877-1889 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Davidson to Plass, 1873; 1881-1889 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - CL Kimball to Plass, 1880-1888 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Edward Paul to Plass, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - HB Willits to Plass, 1878-1887 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - HB Willits to Plass, 1881-1882 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - HB Willits to Plass, 1883-1889 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Plass Miscellaneous, 1878-1886 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Subseries 6.5: Viola and Company, 1882-1885
    - Viola and Company to Clove Spring Iron Works, 1882-1885 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- 7. Sylvan Lake, 1871-1885
  - Subseries 7.1: Finances, 1871-1884
    - Receipted Bills, 1873-1879 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Receipted Bills, 1882-1884 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letter Receipts, 1876-1884 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Transportation Charges, 1871-1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Statements, 1871-1883 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Weights of Iron Shipped, 1871-1883 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Wage Rates, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Boarding Payments, 1874-1881 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 7.2: Correspondence, 1871-1884
    - Receipted Bills, 1873-1879 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Receipted Bills, 1882-1884 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Letter Receipts, 1876-1884 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Transportation Charges, 1871-1879 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Statements, 1871-1883 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Weights of Iron Shipped, 1871-1883 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Wage Rates, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Boarding Payments, 1874-1881 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 7.3: Miscellaneous, 1873-1885
    - Court Order for John Buckley, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Report of Materials Received at the Sylvan Lake Mine, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Inquiry regarding creditworthiness of employee, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Beekman Furnace Company, 1873-1881 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- 8. Crocker Brothers, 1874-1888
  - Subseries 8.1: Finances, 1878-1883
    - Statements of payment between Crocker Bros. and CSIW, 1878 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - CSIW account with Crocker Brothers, 1880-1883 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - CSIW account with Crocker Brothers, 1880-1882 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Transportation Charges, 1880-1882 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Financial Calculations Unspecified, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 8.2: Correspondence, 1874-1888
    - CSIW and Crocker Brothers, 1874-1888 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Letters to E.W. Plass, 1877-1879 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Letters to E.W. Plass, 1880-1882 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- 9. Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad, 1874-1888
  - Subseries 9.1: Finances, 1878-1904
    - Bills, 1878-1879 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bills, 1880-1888 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Financial Correspondence, 1879-1896 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Financial Correspondence, 1901-1904 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 9.2: Correspondence, 1881-1903
    - Telegraphs, 1881-1903 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Wells to NJ Plass, 1881-1885 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 9.3: The Philadelphia Reading and New England Railroad Company, 1888-1902
    - Shares and Mortgage Bonds, 1891-1902 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Letter Receipts, 1896-1899 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Bills, 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Fowler (lawyer) to Brock, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Fowler to Brock, 1890-1902 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Fazende and Seixas to Brock, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Fazende and Seixas telegraphs, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Appleton to Brock, 1898-1900 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Appleton to Brock, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Letters to Brock, 1888-1899 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Invitation to Board Meetings, 1885-1890 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- 10. Administrative, 1872-1898
  - Subseries 10.1: Orders, 1872-1898
    - Administrative Supplies (Willits to Plass), 1879-1888 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Order Conflicts, 1872-1873; 1881 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Orders, 1872-1885 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 10.2: Legal, 1872-1887
    - Legal Matters (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - T. Coffin (lawyer) to Reid, 1875-1876 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Lease Agreements, 1872-1873 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Contracts, 1873-1875; 1887 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 10.3: Finances, 1872-1898
    - Insurance, 1872-1884 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Taxes, 1874-1885; 1898 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Annual Reports, 1881-1886 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Bond Issues, 1873-1874 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Subseries 10.4: Miscellaneous, 1873-1889
    - Surveys, 1873-1883 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Census Statistics, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Meetings, 1878; 1883; 1889 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Use of House Space Agreement (Box 6, Folder 32)
- 11. Operations, 1872-1898
  - Subseries 11.1: Broken Equipment and Repairs, 1872-1898
    - Broken Equipment and Repairs, 1872-1878 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 11.2: Broken Equipment, Supplies and Repairs, 1881-1888
    - Broken Equipment, Supplies and Repairs, 1881-1888 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 11.3: Shipping, 1876-1888
    - Shipping, 1876-1888 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 11.4: Receipt of Shipments, 1881-1881
    - Receipt of Shipments, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 11.5: Bills, 1873-1881
    - Bills, 1873; 1880-1881 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 11.6: Horses, Hay and Feed, 1873-1885
    - Horses, Hay and Feed, 1873-1885 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 11.7: Requests for Iron Statistics, 1883-1889
    - Requests for Iron Statistics, 1883-1889 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 11.8: Requests for Iron Statistics, 1878-1878
    - Loaned Coal Statements, November 1878 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 11.9: Construction, 1890-1890
    - Construction, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 11.10: CSIW Blueprints, 1892-1892
    - CSIW Blueprints, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- 12. Coal, 1872-1888
  - Subseries 11.1: Offers of Coal/Wood, 1873-1886
    - Offers of Coal/Wood, 1873-1886 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 11.2: Offers of Coal/Wood, 1882-1882
    - Offers of Coal/Wood, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 11.3: Coal/Wood Orders, 1875-1888
    - Offers of Coal/Wood, 1875-1888 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 11.4: Receipt of delivery/payment, 1874-1875
    - Receipt of delivery/payment (coal), 1874-1875 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 11.5: Correspondence Regarding Coal Accounts, 1873-1885
    - Correspondence Regarding Coal Accounts, 1873; 1884-1885 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 11.6: Statements of Charcoal Received, 1874-1874
    - Statements of Charcoal Received, 1874 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 11.7: Conflict with Coal, 1879-1879
    - Conflict with Coal, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 11.8: Charcoal and Wood Contracts, 1870-1874
    - Charcoal and Wood Contracts, 1870-1874 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 11.9: Charcoal and Wood Contracts, 1875-1877
    - Charcoal and Wood Contract, 1875-1877 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 11.10: Wood Contracts, 1873-1873
    - Wood Contracts, 1873 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 11.11: Wood and Hauling Contracts, 1874-1874
    - Wood and Hauling Contracts, 1874 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 11.12: Ore Analysis, 1880-1885
    - Ore Analysis, 1880-1885 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- 13. Miscellaneous, 1880-1892
  - Subseries 12.1: Companies, 1880-1892
    - Ozone MFG Co., 1890-1892 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Albany and Rensselaer Iron and Steel Company, 1880-1881 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 12.2: CompaniesOriginal Finding Aid (names)
    - Original Finding Aid (names) (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 12.3: Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 25)